Charlotte J. Lambert

cjl8@illinois.edu · charlottelambert.github.io

Research Objective

My research aims to make online spaces more welcoming to its users through the encouragement of healthy behaviors and improved methods of moderation. Broadly, my interests are at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction and Natural Language Processing. Currently, my focus is on examining factors that contribute to healthy and unhealthy online conversations. Specifically, I am working on devising proactive methods to facilitate online conversations that are resilient to the influence of adverse behavior.

Keywords: Online communities, social computing, healthy behaviors, moderation

Education

• University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Ph.D. in Computer Science

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan

Research Interests: Social Computing, Natural Language Processing

• Vassar College
Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, Minors in Mathematics and Italian; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Poughkeepsie, NY
2016-2020

- Thesis: Temporal Exploration of the Proceedings of Old Bailey

Research Advisors: Jonathan Gordon and Jennifer Walter

Publications

• Conversational Resilience: Quantifying and Predicting Conversational Outcomes Following Adverse Events. In the 16th International Conference on Web and Social Media

Charlotte Lambert, Ananya Rajagopal, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Inter-Sense: An Investigation of Sensory Blending in Fiction. In First International Workshop on Multisensory Data & Knowledge: The 3rd Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

• Story Immersion: Toward Fiction Synesthesia for Enhanced Reader Empathy. Presentation in Uncommon Senses Conference (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

Awards and Honors

• **Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign 2020-2021 *Fellowship awarded to outstanding graduate students in computer science.*

• **Graduated with Departmental Honors**, Vassar College Honors awarded to students nominated by the Computer Science Department for academic excellence.

• Graduated with General Honors, Vassar College 2020

Graduated with General Honors, vassar Conlege
 Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class.
 Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination, Vassar College

• Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination, Vassar College
Awarded to graduating seniors nominated based upon their research accomplishments and academic record.

Research Experience

Graduate Research Assistant
 Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Fall 2021 - present

2020

Urbana, IL

2020-present

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan

Project: Conversation-Level Resilience to Bad Actors in Reddit Communities

Area of Work: Human-Computer Interaction

Undergraduate Research Assistant
Department of Computer Science, Vassar College

Poughkeepsie, NY 2018-2020

- Advisor: Jonathan Gordon; Project: Computational Models of Literary Variation
- Assisted on projects related to natural language processing
- Analyzed patterns in data collected about the use of language in a corpus of books
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing

Distributed Research Experiences for Undergraduates (DREU) Intern Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Summer 2019

- Advisor: Julia Hockenmaier; Project: Collaborative Dialogue in Minecraft
- Started building fully interactive agents to communicate using natural language in a 3D environment
- Used concepts in NLP and deep learning to improve quality of utterances generated by two agents
- Worked on neural network to recognize shapes in 3D with nearly 100% accuracy
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Intern University of Southern California Institute for Creative Technologies

Los Angeles, CA Summer 2018

- Advisor: Jonathan Gratch, Gale Lucas; Project: Impact of AI on User Psychology
- Developed and optimized code to support a system to be used to carry out a future study
- Worked to create realistic AI capable of negotiating online with users and other AIs
- Area of Work: Artificial Intelligence

Teaching Experience

Discrete Math (CS 173)
 University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Teaching Assistant, Instructors: Dr. Margaret Fleck, Dr. Carl Evans
 Spring 2021, Summer 2021
 Guide weekly group discussions for seven groups of approx. 6 students; Evaluate weekly exams; Hold weekly office

• Introduction to Computer Science (CS 125)

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Dr. Geoffrey Challen

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Fall 2020

Co-led an optional weekly recap of course material for between 50 and 100 undergraduates.

Professional Service and Volunteering

Reviewer

International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM) 2022, Atlanta, GA

Girls Who Code Facilitator

2021-present

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Sub-reviewer

"AAAI-MAKE: Combining Machine Learning and Knowledge Engineering Practice," AAAI Spring Symposium 2020, Stanford University

Languages

Italian (proficient); Spanish (reading)

Programming

Python, Java, LATEX, C/C++, R, Matlab, Dr Racket/Scheme